Hi everybody. Today is Saturday, October
25th, 2025 and our friend John Kiriakou
is back with us. Welcome back, John.
Thank you so much, Nima. Good to see
you.
Please subscribe and hit like button and
and please follow John. The links to his
YouTube channels is in the description.
And John,
can you tell us what is the name of
these YouTube channels that they can
find in the description?
>> Sure. Sure, the the bigger of the two is
called Deep Focus with John Kiriakou. We
have the same kinds of conversations
that you and I have and the uh the other
one is called The DeProgram Show. That's
with John Kiriakou and Ted Rall. We do
that every morning and we talk about the
day's news.
Great. Thank you.
John, let me start with the current
situation between the United States, the
West, and Russia. We've learned from
Reuters, they're talking about the new
package of sanctions to be imposed on
Russia by the end of this month, if I'm
not mistaken. It was introduced 3 days
ago.
And the main goal of these sanctions
are
the Russian oil
infrastructure and the bank system, the
bank the bank you know, the the the
sector of the banking of Russia, that
they the communication they have with
the other countries and Zelenskyy's
pushing for
you know, total disconnection of Russia
with dollar.
And what we've learned 5 months ago, 6
months ago from Russian president that
he said that they have reduced their
dependence on dollar
from 54%
to 13%
5 or 6 months ago.
And
here is what Donald Trump said about the
new sanctions and how he feels about
them.
Putin basically said today that Russia
is immune from US sanctions. He said
that it would not impact the Russian
economy in any serious way. Is he wrong?
>> glad I'm glad he feels that way. That's
good. I'll let you know about it in 6
months from now, okay? Let's see. Let's
see how it all works out.
[Music]
John, just look at Pete Hoekstra,
please, here.
The reality
>> economy in any serious way. Is he wrong?
>> I'm glad he feels that way. That's good.
I'll let you know about it in 6 months
from now, okay? Let's see. Let's see how
it all works out.
Yeah, it's something
Yeah.
What's your take? What's your
understanding of this sort of strange
behavior? Bizarre, it's so bizarre and I
don't know if we have any sort of, you
know, explanation for that. What's your
take on what's going on?
You know, it seems to me, Nima, that
this is like an administration without a
policy. And even worse than that, it's
it's an administration without an idea
of what the policy should be.
Either you're going to be
neo-conservative or you're not. You're
going to be
MAGA,
America first. So, one or the other.
This issue with sanctions, it's as
though
it's as though the administration
doesn't really understand
that sanctions have less and less and
less of an effect every time you use
them. For example,
immediately after the Russian invasion
of Ukraine, we piled sanctions on Russia
with the idea being that we would
paralyze the ruble and make such an
economic catastrophe in Russia that the
Russians would have to pull out.
Well,
since the invasion and the sanctions,
the ruble is up 40%
against the dollar. 40%. The Russians
have turned instead to the Chinese.
The Chinese have developed their own
Swift system. So, these banking
transactions no longer go through New
York, they go through Shanghai, which
makes the Russians immune
to American financial sanctions.
So, we have sanctioned other countries
to the point where
the sanctions don't have any effect. The
sanctions don't work. Just this morning,
we sanctioned
um
uh President Petro of uh Colombia and
his family only because he said
something that made Donald Trump angry.
That was it. And now we have sanctions
on one of our closest allies in the
Western Hemisphere.
It doesn't make any sense. We're we're
preparing to sanction Canada.
We're preparing to sanction Ireland.
Uh the none of this makes any sense
anymore. Um I've long been opposed to
sanctions as a foreign policy weapon.
Look at Iran as another example. And
forgive me if I'm repeating myself here.
But we have had sanctions on Iran for 47
years.
47 years. Yet, if you go to Iran, and I
have friends who are in Iran right now,
you'll see daily life in the street
being completely normal. Why? Because
the Russians have strong economic
relationships with with the Iranians,
rather. Strong relationships with
Russia, with China, with India. Iran is
a member of the BRICS now.
They don't they don't need the United
States. And because they've been so
heavily sanctioned by the United States
over so many years,
they've had decades to work around those
sanctions.
It seems to me that every time the
United States places sanctions on a
country,
it makes us a little bit weaker.
It reminds me of
Donald Trump before being elected in the
United States. He said the same thing.
Why do we need to have to put sanctions
on Iran and Russia?
And that would hurt us and you see
Donald Trump is totally different from
what it was before. Mhm. And who are
these people, John?
I
I I I
you know, I think you know that there is
a video in which Putin said that after
anybody is elected, it doesn't matter
Republican, Democrat, the people in dark
suits come in and they give them the
plan. This is the plan.
Who are these people?
Well, I think the most obvious ones are
Republican members of the US Senate.
We can talk about the deep state,
certainly. But in terms of policy and
the formulation of policy,
the people who have the most effect, the
most impact, the most influence with
Donald Trump are Republican members of
the US Senate. Because just like members
of the deep state, they're not going
anywhere.
I mean, we reelect 96% of our members of
Congress, 98% of the Senate, 96% of the
House. And so,
those senators are going to be there
long after Donald Trump leaves.
So, what they do, what they are doing is
trying to force
a neo-conservative foreign policy
back into the White House and the State
Department. And while they failed in the
first Trump administration, they're
largely succeeding now. All of a sudden,
Donald Trump is doing things that MAGA
Republicans should be furious about. And
instead, it's just traditional
Republican foreign policy sneaking back
in. And it's because, I think, of
Republican senators.
Yeah.
These Republicans that you mentioned, um
it seems that you're talking about
people like Lindsey Graham and Ted Cruz
and these people. How how in the world
Donald Trump would side with them
against, you know,
you remember during the Russia gate,
few Republicans
supported Donald Trump. Few. And you
know, and one of them, one of the most,
you know,
you know, one of the the
Republicans was Rand Paul that he did
everything to support Donald Trump.
Donald Trump right now is turning, you
know, he's just attacking him. People in
Kentucky, don't vote him, you know, just
remove him from
What is this sort of relationship? How?
Because
from what I
my understanding of Donald Trump is
anybody who
seems friendly to him is going to
support him. But that's not the case for
Rand Paul. That's not the case for these
people like
Ted
Tucker Carlson.
Who Who decides about these sort of
policies? Not personal, it's beyond
that.
>> It is. It's beyond that. And isn't it
interesting that it's only now that so
many Republicans, especially
conservative Republicans,
are comfortable enough or feel safe
enough to begin disagreeing with Donald
Trump over US policy toward Israel, for
example.
It really has been Tucker Carlson that
has led that fight.
Uh it's it's refreshing.
But I think And I think we're going to
see more of it after the midterm
elections.
Because Donald Trump Here's the bottom
line. The bottom line is Donald Trump is
a lame duck.
Donald Trump cannot run for president
again. He's done. The Constitution is
very, very clear. He can't run again.
And a lot of Republicans believe that
once Donald Trump departs the scene,
the Republican Party as a party is going
to return
to
a neo-conservative policy that it has
maintained
since the end of the Second World War,
really. So, Lindsey Graham is going to
become the old Lindsey Graham again, as
horrible as that sounds. Ted Cruz is
going to talk about invading other
countries like he used to talk about all
the time.
And all of these people who have been
worried
that Donald Trump may damage their
re-election efforts or may say something
mean about them
or may support a primary
opponent running against them,
they're all going to
go back to the way things were, feel
free to criticize, even to criticize
Donald Trump. They're just biting their
time.
Once they get past this next election,
which is a year from
Well, it's a year and a week from now.
Um
Donald Trump is going to be an
afterthought.
Even Barack Obama, who was far more
popular than Donald Trump, even he
realized that he was essentially done
being president after year six.
Do you think that
this situation with Russia would lead to
new escalations because
in this new sort of sanctions, is this
new package, they're talking about
hitting the Russian oil infrastructure.
They were attacked physically by
Ukrainians.
And which we know when we talk about
Ukrainians, we have to consider that the
targets, the intelligence all came from
the United States and the British.
And they attacked them physically and
they're trying to sanction them,
you know, two sort of different attacks
on their oil infrastructure. What is
that Do you think we are heading toward
new escalations in Ukraine?
>> I do. And I'll tell you why.
Well, besides the fact that the that the
neo-conservatives are re-establishing
themselves, I've spoken over the last
two weeks with some of the most
important
thinkers on the issue of Russian studies
uh
here in Washington, the chairman of the
history department at uh at American
University and a Russia expert and the
the founder of the nuclear studies
program, for example.
Um
and every one of these experts that I
speak with say the same thing, which is
remarkable. They say it independently of
one another.
And that is that the war is essentially
over. Russia has won.
Right? The the Russians although they're
advancing slowly,
they're advancing. And every day they
lose a little bit more territory. And so
it's not in Russia's interest to end
this war.
Why would they want to? They're winning.
Well, the only way that you can force
the Russians to the negotiating table is
to push them back. And the only way to
push them back is to use American
intelligence, British intelligence,
German intelligence, and
NATO hardware
that you're giving to the to the
Ukrainians to push them back. If you
can't push them back physically on the
ground, which the Ukrainians cannot,
and NATO, of course, can't provide
troops because then that would be a
declaration of war,
you have them do something that is
almost as dangerous,
and that is to strike Russian
infrastructure, especially oil and gas
infrastructure.
I think that would be a catastrophic
error on the part of the West because it
ratchets up the level of violence in
this war.
And I think that we should then expect
to see some sort of a of a Russian
response. You know, during the Vietnam
War,
one of the complaints that the United
States had was that the Russians and the
Chinese were were arming and funding the
North Vietnamese. Well, of course they
were
because they wanted to push the United
States out.
Well, now, if we
are are continuing to arm and fund the
Ukrainians,
the Russians are going to make it worse
for Ukraine and worse for us.
The only way to go is up in escalation,
and that's
a very bad thing.
I think one of the realistic signs of
what to what's because with the Trump
administration, you cannot find out what
is the policy, what would be the policy
in the next 24 hours.
>> Right.
And but when it comes to Russians, we
have seen some sort of consistency in
their sort of message.
And
that is hugely problematic when it comes
to the latest escalations because we see
Putin just warning the United States and
the West with, you know, shocking and
staggering response
from Russia to any attack on Russia on
on deep into the Russian soil.
But
Medvedev also came out and said, "This
the United States is our enemy." Yes.
The main outcome of these new sanctions,
that shows you for those those of you
who are delusional and delusional about,
you know, what's going on between the
United States and Russia, you have to
understand that the enemy is the United
States.
These are not signs. No. I You know, I
I'm one of these people, Nima, who is
eternally optimistic.
And even I am not seeing any reasons for
optimism. One thing about Medvedev, too,
I was just talking to a to a Russian
um about him yesterday.
Here in the West, so many people think
Medvedev is a loose cannon. He's a kind
of crazy, he's always on Twitter.
He does that on purpose.
He Medvedev is the one who puts the
Russian policy position out there in the
public for the West to read.
He's not just, you know, sitting on his
on the edge of his bed just, you know,
tweeting on his phone.
This is what his instructions are. He's
the one that's out there
floating Russian policy positions while
Putin acts more presidential. The only
thing that gives me optimism right now
is that at least Trump and Putin are
talking.
Biden and Putin didn't talk.
There was a report in the New York Times
at the beginning of this past week that
even
Melania Trump picked up the hot phone
and spoke with Putin about, I don't
know, some women's rights issue. That's
incredible to me.
Can you imagine Jill Biden picking up
the phone and calling Putin and having
an actual conversation? So, at least we
have that. At least we have
dialogue, even if the dialogue is not
yet getting us anywhere.
Um
you know, I have a lot of problems with
a lot of Donald Trump's policies, but in
this case, really, we should let Trump
be Trump and try to work out a deal
to to get this war behind us.
The main issue, John, in the latest
you know, meeting between the two in
Alaska,
Yes.
>> Anchorage in Alaska, they were talking
about this
ceasefire and
if you remember, Donald Trump came out
of the meeting, he said that there would
be no ceasefire. We have to find
permanent solution for the situation.
But he came back to the same position
that he he had before the meeting. Mhm.
He's talking again about an immediate
ceasefire,
which is not accepted, which is not the
case for Russia.
>> to happen.
Yeah, you're right.
And
the other point, John, when you have
some sort of chaos in the communication
you have with your counterpart, which
would be Russia,
there is a lot
happening behind the scene. You know, if
something like what has happened to
nuclear bombers of Russia happens by
British intelligence, by Polish
intelligence,
something is
how can you control that?
Is that the case that anybody concerned
in your opinion in the Trump
administration that could happen or they
don't care about it? So, what would
Russia do? The last time they we did it,
they didn't respond, they didn't do
anything. That was a terrorist terrorist
attack.
But these, you know, Russia is what
seems to me from the Russian part,
they're so patient. But it gets to a
moment that's going to be explosive.
The same happened with the case of
Ukraine, John. Since 2014 up until 2022,
they were trying to be patient,
negotiating.
And it came to a point that there is no
point for negotiation with the West.
Let's go and fight.
Yeah.
>> This is hugely concerning, in my
opinion. I I agree with you. I agree
with you. You know, it it was very funny
to me, funny to the point where I
actually laughed out loud when I read
the report in in the Washington Post
that here we are disagreeing with the
Russians almost every day, and it's
headlines. We disagree on on
arms transfers to the Ukrainians, we
disagree on the use of drones, we
disagree on this, we disagree on that.
The Russians send a bomber inside
American airspace.
And then the Russians say, "We're in
talks with the United States to to uh
build a bridge connecting uh Russia with
Alaska. And it's going to be called the
Putin-Trump Bridge."
It's like, "What? what are you talking
about?
There's not going to be any bridge
collecting Russian connecting Russia and
and Alaska. Why even say such a thing?
Well, they throw that out there because
they want people to understand that
while the headlines are bad
at least we're still talking.
Now, with that said
Marco Rubio, I'm not a fan of Marco
Rubio. I never have been. Marco Rubio is
a classic Republican neo-conservative.
And a lot of it is because of his
personal background. His family fled
Cuba. He's staunchly anti-communist. A
lot of Republicans still think that the
Russians are communists. As crazy as
that sounds, a lot of them still believe
that.
And now, not only is Rubio
Secretary of State, he's also the
National Security Advisor and he has
traditionally and consistently
exhibited weakness in front of Donald
Trump.
You may remember the the 2016 debates
where Trump called him little Marco
Rubio.
And
and said in in public in the first
debate that Rubio was so afraid to
debate him that he was standing in a
puddle of his own piss.
Well, how much respect is involved
in a statement like that?
I think Rubio is afraid of Trump. So,
what what we're seeing right now is a
Trump foreign policy affected not by
Rubio and Rubio's ideology, but by the
ideology of Rubio's former colleagues in
the Senate.
It's the traditional Republican foreign
policy that's being forced on Trump
through Rubio.
John, let's dig deeper in the Trump
administration in terms of the
intelligence that he's receiving.
Because we I don't know if he tries to
say something different from what he's
hearing or he literally receives, you
know, false information.
I remember when we learned that Tulsi
Gabbard going to be in the
administration, we were so optimistic
that she's going to change the tone in
Washington.
But so far, who's who's
you know
the mastermind of the intelligence
that's getting to the Donald Trump
getting to the Trump administration
getting to Donald Trump himself?
Is that Tulsi Gabbard? It doesn't seem
to me because
just
remembering what has happened with the
case of Iran when Tulsi Gabbard said
there is no sign, no any evidence that
Iran is going beyond the program the
peaceful program they have. They don't
they're not
they haven't
you know, they haven't gone after, you
know, nuclear bombs. There there is no
sign for us to to to state that. But
Donald Trump said
he doesn't care about what Tulsi Gabbard
said. He has his own mind.
Right.
>> But it doesn't seem to me that he has
his own mind. Somebody's providing him
with information. Who's that?
I think you're right.
In fact, I know you're right because
when Donald Trump commissioned a
national intelligence estimate
on the Russia gate, he calls it the
Russia gate hoax. I agree it's a hoax.
Um
and the CIA prepared a paper
saying, you know, this is what we found.
Uh
he fired literally everybody
that had something to do with the paper.
Now, the CIA is different from the rest
of the federal government in that it
does not have the same
uh Civil Service Act protections that
the rest of the government has. At the
CIA
um these tell us all the time, we serve
at the pleasure of the president.
And so, if the president doesn't like
your face or he doesn't like your tie
he can fire you and there's nothing you
can do about it. You can't go to the to
the union. You can't you can't uh
go to the Merit Systems Protection Board
and ask for a second chance. You're out.
They take your badge, they walk you to
your car and you drive away and never
come back.
So
we know at least in that example
that he was getting
his intelligence from Tulsi Gabbard and
he hated it. He hated what the
intelligence was. Interestingly enough
the intelligence that goes from the CIA
to Donald Trump doesn't go through Tulsi
Gabbard so much as it goes through John
Ratcliffe.
But John Ratcliffe has been immune so
far.
Uh one of the things that I heard
recently is John Ratcliffe and why what
in the world would
would make him do such a thing? But I
heard recently that John Ratcliffe has
been consulting with John Brennan
about what intelligence should go to the
president. Why in God's name
would you consult someone like John
Brennan
knowing that the president hates John
Brennan more than anybody else in
America
and is actively seeking to prosecute
him?
See, but that's what the deep state is.
It's this amorphous blob that never goes
anywhere and never changes and knows
that Donald Trump's only going to be
president for 3 more years and they can
outwait him.
So, I think that he's getting his
intelligence from several different
places. I think he's getting it from the
intelligence community, whether it's DNI
or CIA.
I think he's getting it from Fox News
and maybe Newsmax, but most likely Fox
News. And I think the people who are
close to him whisper into his ear things
that they know he wants to hear.
And that's how he formulates policy.
That's why we see policy constantly
moving back and forth.
What is our China policy? I can give you
10 different answers and none of them
have anything to do with the other
because it changes all the time. And it
changes on what the last person
whispered into Donald Trump's ear
and what he saw on Fox News.
How do you evaluate the role of Stephen
Miller? Oh, I think Stephen Miller is
very, very important. Very important in
this administration. And you know that
this is a different Steve Miller than
what we saw in the first uh
right all the time.
Well, we know that Stephen Miller is the
architect of the immigration policy.
He's the architect of the border policy.
He's the architect of the Israel policy.
Yet, he never speaks publicly anymore.
He was on TV the other day and I
actually didn't recognize him.
He lives in the same town that I live
in, Arlington, Virginia. And last week
he sold his house and moved and we don't
know where because
pro-immigration demonstrators were
marching in front of the house and
writing messages in chalk on the
on the sidewalk. So, he literally sold
his house and moved.
It's a different Stephen Miller. It's a
quiet, private Stephen Miller who's
who's making policy behind the scenes
where the rest of us aren't supposed to
see the sausage being made.
John, do you see how do you see the
connection between the British
intelligence and the intelligence in the
United CIA?
Or do they coordinate what they want to
do, for example, in Ukraine with the
United States or they have some sort of
independence
to do that?
>> they they coordinate very, very closely.
In fact, you know, I was giving a
I I gave a speaking tour. I had a
speaking tour all around the United
Kingdom at the start of the year and one
of the people that I was conversant with
on stage was a retired MI6 officer. And
we used to talk about exactly this
question.
And he said, you know, we never minded
being the little brother to the CIA
except when the CIA goes out and starts
killing people. Then we disagree and we
didn't want anything to do with that.
Otherwise, everything we do
is coordinated with the CIA.
Actually, I think the opposite.
Well, I he didn't want to talk about
India or or Africa. So, I have to agree
with you. I think the opposite, too.
But
John,
the case of Ukraine is so much important
for the British government for many
reasons because the rise of Zelenskyy is
the production of the British policy.
Yes. The British did they they produced
Zelenskyy. You know, you have a
as you we have a literally a far-right
government in Kiev. Yes. They're they're
mostly, you know
even on CNN if you've seen that you
know, the high Hitler in their sign, you
know, it's unbelievably you
and you put a
Jew as the head of these people. Yeah.
And this only the this sort of plan
comes from the British.
And they
every time Zelenskyy comes to the United
States Washington talking with Donald
Trump in the aftermath he goes to the
United Kingdom. Always. Same has
happened
just two days ago. Yes.
What are they what is the leverage? What
are they trying to do which would be
different from what the United States
wants to do with Ukraine in Europe?
Well, the British policy really comes
down to where that Boris Johnson said it
was
three or four years ago.
Right? It was Boris Johnson that made
sure that there was no change in policy
and the British were going to drag the
Americans whether it was, you know,
willingly or kicking and screaming to
ensure that this war did not end.
Right? The idea is to is to keep the
Russians fighting. You know this old
joke that that we're going to fight to
the last Ukrainian.
Well, it's it's said because it's true.
The idea is to do to the Russians what
the Russians did to us in Vietnam.
Or what we did to the Russians in
Afghanistan.
Right? Fight to the last Russian. If
they have to bring in troops from North
Korea or for China,
kill them, too. But the idea is just to
drain the Russians, to bankrupt Russia.
And that's not really working out.
Well, of course, Zelenskyy and whoever
happens to be British Prime Minister on
any given day,
and God knows they've had a lot of them.
Um the idea is to make sure that there's
no change in that policy that Boris
Johnson set out years ago.
I I think the
the case of Ukraine
Let me put it this way. The two
projects, Ukraine project and Israel
project, both are are the production of
the British Empire.
In my
>> Yeah, without any question.
And and
May I add something? May I add something
that's very topical? It's not just
Ukraine-Russia, Israel-Palestine.
Just yesterday I was having a
conversation about the border skirmish
that resulted in as many as 200 dead
between
Pakistan and Afghanistan.
And the Durand Line was drawn by the
British.
The British created that border. That
border is not recognized by any of the
tribes.
You know, look at the Pashtuns. They
have family members on one side of the
border, family members on the other side
of the border.
And the British just drew a line between
them.
What gives the British the right now or
100 years ago or 200 years ago? What
gave the British the right to decide
where where borders should be?
And so here we are more than a century
later, and we still have problems.
Deadly, serious problems
because of this British imperialist
arrogance.
Which Do you think the British are doing
the same that they've done to themselves
to the United to the US Empire? Oh, I
do. I do think so.
The British egged us on. The British
want us to be the policeman of the
world.
And they don't really care if it if it
weakens the United States over the long
run.
They willingly gave up their empire
after the Second World War because they
were bankrupt. And that's exactly when
the US was ascendant and we were
creating our new empire.
And so, you know, they're the little
brother now to the United States.
They prefer to go along for the ride.
Yeah.
John, is that
if we focus a little bit on Ukraine, do
you think the case
with
Zelenskyy, because one of the main
issues being addressed by the Russians
so far is the Zelenskyy cannot be in
power because he's not the legitimate
president of Ukraine. But if we go
beyond that, who cares about who's going
to run Ukraine if you change Zelenskyy
with Zaluzhnyy, which is the former
commander of Ukrainian Army, Right.
which is now the Ukrainian ambassador to
the United Kingdom, which is prepared if
they want to change Zelenskyy, he's
going to be
Right. the same story. Well, you know,
Putin is right that
according to the Ukrainian Constitution,
it's actually
not legitimate. It's not legal for
Zelenskyy to still be in this position.
Zelenskyy, of course, has suspended
elections because the country is in a
time of war, but
the Ukrainian Constitution is clear that
you can't just suspend the Constitution
indefinitely.
Um I agree with you. Zaluzhnyy is the is
the person who would probably be
installed or elected
uh to replace Zelenskyy. The British
would be thrilled with that. The
Americans likely would also be thrilled
with it. But I think that they don't
want to
allow the Russians even that small
victory of pushing Zelenskyy out. And
that's why they're not they're not
demanding new elections.
Let me say I'm amazed by the ability of
the intelligence community in the West,
the way that they're preparing. You
know, looking at Zaluzhnyy when the way
it was, you know, the commander with,
you know, this
right now with the beautiful suit and,
you know, he's like an actor. The new
photos coming out. The same has happened
with the al-Julani in Syria. Yes. You
know, they literally
turn a, you know,
a guy butcher into a president. Member
of al-Qaeda,
founding co-leader of ISIS,
and then we decide, "No, no, this is the
guy we're going to work with."
You know, I I've said, and maybe this is
controversial, but I've said from the
beginning,
you don't just flip like that overnight.
He has to have been a CIA source
of long standing
for the United States all of a sudden to
say, "Uh we're going to go with this
guy. We're going to go with this ISIS
guy
because he's the one that we can work
with. He's the moderate." And then, like
magic, like that, the United States
lifts sanctions against Syria, where
they were literally dancing in the
street.
And then we said, "Well, but you have to
protect religious minorities." Right?
Christians and and Druze and uh
you know, Jews, there's a handful of
Jews still in Damascus, whomever. And
they say, "Yes, yes, we're going to
protect religious minorities." And then
they start killing everybody.
And we say, "Well,
that's a shame, but we have to look at
the bigger picture and
and he's our guy."
Donald Trump, it seems that the Trump
administration has some sort of
differences with Netanyahu
administration in terms of the peace
plan, so-called peace plan. Peace plan
is not it's not a pause. It's a It is.
Peace plan is not any
There is no no sign of peace plan.
>> Correct.
But
we had
the Vice President of the United States,
J.D. Vance, and then Rubio going to
Israel.
Donald Trump himself said that the
annexation of the West Bank is not going
to happen under the Trump
administration. But Netanyahu,
he said in Hebrew with the Israeli
media, he said, "They always say that.
And
don't worry about that doesn't That's
not important because we are an
independent nation." Right. Is Israel an
independent nation in your opinion?
Oh, yeah.
I think Israel controls the United
States, not not the the reverse.
Um you know, the the Knesset uh in
committee, they voted 25 to 24 this week
to annex the West Bank.
Historically, that has been an
unacceptable position for the United
States since 1967.
But
but
the Israelis have such incredible
control over US foreign policy.
And the Democrats are even more
pro-Israel than the Republicans are.
I wouldn't be surprised if what
Netanyahu said was true. "Uh the
Americans, they always say that. They're
going to fall into line."
I bet they do fall into line.
What was the response when the Israelis
annexed the Golan Heights? Nobody said a
word.
Nobody said a single word.
I mean, the Israelis essentially
de facto have annexed the West Bank.
They just cleared out a Christian
village two, three weeks ago to make
room for new settlers from New Jersey,
New York, Toronto. Just Ahlan wa Sahlan.
Come on in.
Pick any house you want. It's yours now.
Well, what is that? How How is the
United the United States supposed to be
the honest broker?
We we can't be when our foreign policy
is controlled by Israel.
Donald Trump in his speech at the
Knesset said that he had no idea about,
you know, moving the embassy
to Jerusalem. Please. Sheldon Adelson
paid for it.
Yeah.
Sheldon Adelson paid for it and they put
a big bronze plaque
uh at the embassy now thanking Donald
Trump and Sheldon Adelson for moving the
embassy from Tel Aviv to Jerusalem. You
know, that bill was passed by Congress
during the Clinton uh administration.
But the bill had a provision that the
president could halt the transfer until
there was a peace agreement between the
Israelis and the Palestinians.
And Donald Trump just said, "Ah, screw
it. We're going to move.
And just did it.
So, we we really have no
we have no
hammer to hold over the Israelis to say,
"Well, listen, if you want if you want
us to move the embassy,
sure, we'll move the embassy, but you
have to make peace with the
Palestinians." Now, they say, "Ah, go
screw yourself.
We do what we want."
John, you've mentioned that the British
intelligence is like a little brother to
the United States CIA. But, how about
Mossad?
Mossad is a little brother or No, no.
No. No, Mossad does anything it wants,
anywhere it wants.
Uh law means nothing. International law
means nothing to Mossad. If they want to
do an operation, they do it. If they
want to kill you, they'll kill you.
If they want to kill you and you happen
to be in an apartment building, they'll
take out the whole city block and kill
everybody on the block if they could be
sure they're going to kill you.
They are utterly, completely, and
totally independent.
You know what's so strange to me, John?
I talked with
Colonel Jacques Baud. Colonel Jacques
Baud, he's he was part of the NATO
operation, the chief of NATO in in
Africa.
I talked with American, you know,
colonels,
and they always say that there is no law
for Israel in military.
Syria.
So,
how how they can have such a leverage on
military if they
they, you know, you're talking about the
the main
the can't, you know, you know, you know,
core of military, they don't agree with
Israel, but they're somehow doing
whatever Israel wants them to do. Yeah.
That comes from Capitol Hill.
The Israelis have been so smart
in the way that they have invested in
American elections since the 1950s, but
really especially beginning in the Nixon
administration around 1969.
They realized, they recognized the the
import of money in American political
races. And so, if you even think
about voting against something that the
Israelis want in Congress, they will
primary you, and they will spend
millions of dollars to beat you to
install a pro-Israel person in your
place. They've been wildly successful. I
mean, this is a an ethnic group that
makes up roughly 2%, less than 2% of the
American population.
But, look at the the power and the
authority that they have, and it's
because of AIPAC and because they so
clearly understand
the American political process better
than anybody else.
You mentioned Nixon, but how about
Carter? I see I don't see Carter be that
much in line with Israel. No.
No, and George H.W. Bush.
When I was serving in Bahrain, I think I
may have mentioned this to you. When I
was serving serving in Bahrain from 1994
to 1996, His Highness the Emir, Sheikh
Isa bin Salman Al Khalifa,
he used to invite
uh diplomats and their families to his
beach house every weekend.
Uh he wanted us to to
feel um uninhibited to wear a bathing
suit, and your wife could wear a bikini
and people wouldn't stare at her, right?
So, we would take our son, I had one
child at the time. We would take our son
to the beach on the weekends, and the
Emir took a a liking to my wife, so he
would invite her for tea, and then a
half an hour later the servant would
come and get me, and
and then I would go sit with him.
And we had a rule at the embassy that
anything the Emir said at the beach was
off-limits and not reportable back to
the State Department.
And he used to talk about these things
all the time.
He said, for example, Carter was good
for the Arabs. He said, "But, the last
president to give the Arabs a fair shake
was George H.W. Bush." When George H.W.
Bush told the Israelis, "Stop building
these settlements," and the Israelis
gave him the finger,
he cut off loan guarantees
until they did stop building the
settlements. Once the the American
voters threw him out of office and
brought in uh um
uh Bill Clinton,
everything started back up again, and
they started building settlements. So,
Eisenhower,
Carter,
and
George H.W. Bush
were really the only three presidents,
well, and and Kennedy uh on the nuclear
issue. We're the only four presidents,
let's say, since the end of the Second
World War to really give the Arabs a
fair a fair shake.
Everybody else is just in the the pocket
of the Israelis politically.
Do you think that the Trump
administration
has some sort of backbone in countering
that, or you see you don't see that much
of, you know, Carter, that much of
George H.W. Bush. Why is that the case?
What where is that backbone in the US
president?
You know, to me there there's this
innate
issue of fairness.
Okay, I I watch the same news that the
president watches, that every president
watches.
And I see what the Israelis are doing to
Palestinians. Human rights mean nothing
to the Israelis.
And they freely will tell you they don't
care about human rights. I do.
Um and other president or some
presidents do.
But, for the most part, it's
millions and millions and millions of
dollars going into campaign coffers
with the likes of Sheldon Adelson
whispering in the ear
of whoever happens to be president, "You
really need to do things the way we want
you to do them. You really need to
support the Israelis."
You know, the first time I went to
Israel, I I went twice in 2022. I'd
never been to Israel before.
And all over the old city of Jerusalem,
you see these posters on the wall
like glued on the walls of buildings,
and it says, "America, we are with you."
And I thought, "Well, what the [__] was
that supposed to mean? With us
in what? How? We don't want you to be
with us.
We want an independent foreign policy."
But, it's like they're trying to
convince us, "Remember, we're your only
true friends in the Middle East," even
though they're not.
It's like they were propagandizing
themselves
to help them propagandize us.
I I really didn't like that at all.
"America, we are with you," and it has a
fist on it.
Like, "Well, what's that supposed to
mean?"
Iranian the head of intelligence of
Iranians said
3 days ago that 50, more than 50
intelligence agency
helped Israel during the 12 days of war
and before the 12 days of war to attack
Iran.
And I remember last time we talked, you
said that Iran has failed in terms of
counterintelligence. But, when you
you're facing such a huge intelligence
against you,
you know, each and every country in the
region, out of the region, in in Europe,
in America, you know, everybody's
against you. What is the solution for
these countries?
Do you think I I talked with Paul Craig
Roberts, one of the solution that he
brings to the table is that
Russia, Iran, and
China, even India. I think what's going
on against India is somehow of concern
because Pakistan, the case of Pakistan,
Bangladesh, the color revolution in
Bangladesh.
Do you think that after all
the behavior of the United States would
bring these countries together?
Yes.
I do. First of all, I think that the
Iranian intelligence chief is correct.
It probably was 50 countries siding with
the with the Israelis.
But, on the Iranian side, the Russians
are good, the Chinese are good, the
Indians are good.
They should have been liaising with the
with the Iraqis, for example. Um the
problem is
that
with the exception of the of the
Russians and the
and the Chinese, those countries don't
really stack up to what the West can
offer, especially
especially technologically.
So,
with that said, I I stand by my original
position that
the Iranians have a counterintelligence
problem. I don't think anybody realized
how deeply infiltrated they had been
with the Israeli recruitment of Afghan
refugees, for example.
Kudos to the Israelis. I would have
never thought of that.
Because you would think, "Well, what
access do the
do these undocumented, you know,
would-be refugees have?" It turned out
they had a lot of access,
especially locational access
related to um Iranian military leaders.
So, I think that the Iranians need to
work hard on counterintelligence and
probably need to strengthen their
liaison relationships with countries
with which they are they're friendly.
Specifically, the Russians, the Chinese,
and the Indians.
Only then, I think, will they be able to
protect themselves
or better protect themselves against the
Israelis.
Every time we hear that there is nothing
going on in the Middle
no war, and everything is going to the
good direction, I really I feel a lot,
you know, that that something big can
happen. Always. Yeah. Always. You know,
I say all the time, if you have access
to Netflix, no matter where you are in
the world, you have to watch this this
series called Fauda.
It's an Israeli series, but it's a joint
Israeli-Palestinian series, and it will
make you both love and hate both sides.
It's so beautifully written and so
exciting.
It really did does give you
a window
into the thinking of both sides of the
conflict.
John,
Israel
the we have two agencies, Mossad and
Shin Bet.
>> Yeah. And the communication between the
two and how much
you know, Mossad is influencing the
foreign policy of Israel, how much Shin
Bet is influencing, how do you see the
communication between these two agencies
and the government in Israel?
>> Yeah, it's all very close. You know,
here in the United States, there's a
there's a a wall between the CIA and the
FBI. The FBI is
just domestic, the CIA is just foreign.
It's it's not so clear in Israel.
Certainly, of course, the Mossad focuses
on foreign intelligence and the Shin Bet
on domestic intelligence, but but
everything bleeds into the other side in
Israel. And so, Mossad and Shin Bet work
very closely together. The very first
briefing I ever gave
at the CIA, this was in like March or
April of 1990,
was to a joint it was a joint briefing
for Mossad and Shin Bet.
Well, overseas,
I I I lived for years overseas.
I couldn't even imagine
going to an intelligence service with
the FBI
for a briefing. I can't imagine even
doing something like that. In fact,
Mossad and Shin Bet do it all the time.
What would be the policy if they want to
if they decide as as we've mentioned
something big would may happen, but if
they decide to attack Iran again,
what is how these intelligence agencies
would convince the, you know, the public
opinion or not the public opinion, the
decision makers in Israel that could
decision could help Israel in a long
run. How much of that sort of, you know,
decision is coming from Mossad and Shin
Bet in your opinion?
In my opinion, a lot of it is coming
from Mossad.
Because remember, the Israelis keep
talking about this existential threat.
They use the word existential all the
time.
That maybe Iran's not a threat today,
and maybe it won't be a threat tomorrow,
but a year from now, 5, 10, 50 years
from now, it's going to be a catastrophe
because eventually Iran is going to get
nuclear weapons and they're going to
fire them at Israel and it's the end of
the world. Right? That's the Israeli
position.
And so,
what the Mossad does, and it does it
quite successfully,
is to convince Israeli policy makers
that that is still the case.
And the policy makers in turn convince
the Israeli public that that is still
the case. And so, you and I both know
that Iran is no threat to Israel. Right?
We both know that.
But the Israelis don't care because
their view of the threat is that it's
existential. It could be 50 years from
now.
So, best to take it take care of it
today by killing every
Iranian nuclear scientist, by taking out
the entire Iranian military leadership,
by overthrowing Ayatollah Khamenei,
whatever they have to do.
Do you remember right before the 12-day
war started, Netanyahu gave this
ridiculous, like embarrassingly silly,
address
to the Iranian people
saying, "We are with you, Iranian
people, and we want to help you, and as
soon as we overthrow your government,
we're going to send 25
experts in water, and we're going to
make the deserts bloom in Iran because
we are with you."
What is that?
I don't know one single Iranian that
took that seriously. It I felt
embarrassed for the Israelis. It was so
silly and ridiculous.
But this is all part of the same policy,
all part of the propaganda.
Yeah.
Every time he talks, he has a picture of
water again. Always drinking water.
Nobody cares about the water. Oh my god.
John, just to wrap up this session,
how last time you said that there is a
possibility of war between the two Iran
and Israel. With the current situation,
we know that the
administration in the United States,
which it seems to me that the mastermind
as Kushner himself that that mastermind
of the new plan in Gaza is a dividing
Gaza in two zones. One zone in the hand
of the United States under Kushner and
Steve Whitcomb on the other part.
Is that going to help the situation? No.
No, not at all. Just like a ceasefire
doesn't help. A ceasefire is not a peace
agreement.
And the Israelis, we know what the
Israelis do with ceasefires because they
do the same thing every day, every time,
rather. They'll wait a couple days and
then they'll blame the Palestinians for
violating the ceasefire and then they
kill another 100 people and then the war
starts again. It's always exactly the
same script that the Israelis follow.
And so, no, I I don't see Tony Blair
bringing
peace and
and prosperity to Gaza just like Steve
Whitcomb and and Jared Kushner are not
going to bring peace and prosperity to
Gaza.
Nobody will until there is an
independent Palestine.
That's the only solution here.
Is there has to be an independent
Palestine.
That's it.
You know, I I mentioned to you, I think
I mentioned it the last time we talked,
maybe the time before,
but Dennis Ross, the former special
envoy for the Middle East peace process,
told me once, around the year 2000, I
guess it was,
I met with him at the State Department
and he said, "There are no new ideas.
Every idea has been thought of and none
of it has worked.
There are no new ideas.
What we have to do is just have the
Palestinians and the Israelis agree on
an idea that they don't really like very
much, but is the least offensive of the
ideas that have been presented." And
what that's going to have to be, you
know, we talk about the one-state
solution, the two-state solution, what
about a three-state solution?
Right? The West Bank Palestinians are an
independent individual entity. The Gaza
Palestinians have, you know, it's a
completely different culture, it's a
different society, they're it's a
different they're different families
in Gaza.
Maybe we need two Palestines.
Because God knows that if the Israelis
absorb both of them, they're not going
to give them the same freedoms that
Israeli citizens have.
So, we're going to have to we're going
to have to force an agreement that
nobody likes, but is the least offensive
to the two sides.
Yeah. Because that would be, John,
hugely problematic because
the West Bank Israelis are they're
already talking about it as,
you know, the annexation of the West
Bank and look at the West Bank,
you know, they have
It's going to end up
it would end up looking like Bosnia,
where there are these little circles on
the map, little circles like pinpricks
all over the map, and those are, you
know,
Serbian
enclaves, for example. Yeah. At this
point, it would have to look like that
in the West Bank.
Yeah. And if I were an Israeli, I
wouldn't want to go anywhere near Gaza.
Thank you so much, John, for being with
us.
>> Great pleasure, as always.
>> It's always great to see you. Thank you.
Thank you.